[Music]
and we are live
good evening good day everyone it's
great to be back with you it's
nice to see you all so today we have a
very
interesting topic aliens ufos are aliens
real are they here
is the us government hiding some proof
and we'll talk also about space travel
does life exist on other worlds
about the moon exploration mars
exploration and much more so
we have an interesting session ahead of
us so let me start with a question for
you all
have you heard of the battle of
nuremberg
so let me show you what there is
so this is the battle of nuremberg it's
a football match
in the 2006 world cup it was between
portugal and the netherlands
and this match was remarkable for
the number of red cards and yellow cards
there were 16 yellow cards
and four red cards it's a ridiculous
match you should see the highlights
on youtube but as you know
i am not here to talk about football
so let me show you what i really am
talking about
so there was a different battle of
nuremberg i'm talking about the original
battle of nuremberg which happened
in the 16th century
so let's take a look at that
so this is what i'm talking about in the
year
1561 there was this
celestial phenomenon over the city of
nuremberg which
is which is the original battle of
nuremberg so what happened is that this
was a mass
sighting of celestial phenomena or ufos
above the city of nuremberg so it was it
was observed by
almost everybody in the city thousands
of people saw it at the same time
it happened on the morning of april 14
at daybreak and
at first it appeared in the middle of
the sun two blood red semicircular arcs
and then there were lots of cylinders
and there was a tri
black triangle and there was filling
cylinders and spheres and object
odd-shaped objects
and there was a kind of battle between
these strange
objects so this is a mass
ufo sighting that happened in 1561
it's a historical sighting and this sort
of
event this sort of sighting which is
observed by thousands of people at the
same
time is very hard to dismiss and it's
not the first time something like this
has happened
such things have happened before as well
and they have happened after this
event as well for example just a few
years ago about a decade or so ago i
believe if not
less there was an event somewhere in
africa where
some sort of an some sort of a ufo is
supposed to have
landed near a school and lots of school
children actually saw this ufo and maybe
even alien beings
so there have been many such reports
of mass sightings by multiple witnesses
of ufos so my position is that it is
one cannot just dismiss these uh
reports of ufo sightings and
and the such on the other hand nowadays
we have this uh this new trend
the us government is trying to
mainstream the
the idea of us4 sightings and they are
releasing certain
pieces of certain clips since there are
certain video clips black and white
video clips
and they are talking about ufos and it's
being mainstream right now the us media
is
very much involved and therefore this
topic is again in the news
so the question is how
believable is this is there any truth to
it are they hiding some information
have they had information about ufos and
aliens in the past
other countries too like the uk have
also reported such sightings
the strange thing is that there are not
so many sightings in other parts of the
world like in
asia etc so it's uh
it's a contentious issue but it's a very
interesting issue because it's a
fascinating thing i mean if aliens
actually exist
and if they've actually visited us i
mean what can be more interesting than
that
it's a fascinating topic and it's
something that brings out the curiosity
and imagination
in all of us so that's what that's one
of the issues we're going to talk about
so let me take some of your questions
about this let's start
this off and take some of your questions
so this question is by jay thunky us
navy has officially admitted
regular sightings of ufos now called
united identified
aerial phenomena and the pentagon has
admitted the existence of classified
programs
for studying these namely aatib yes
so now so these days they are admitting
that they have been studying this
phenomena and they have had
such classified programs in the past uh
such the existence of such
programs has been known to some extent
there was something called project blue
book
in the 60s and 70s and they
it seemed that they were studying such
phenomena so yes
right now they have officially admitted
that such phenomena
have been observed and they are being
studied so that's what
is in the news right now so how true is
that that's the question
right next question
again a declassified report on these uap
studies is due for presentation to us
congress this month what are your
opinions
let's wait and watch i mean we will
know what to think about it only once we
have the information
of this declassified reform report so
let's see what they have to say about
this
i get the feeling that they're trying to
prepare the ground for some sort of
strategic action maybe they want to uh
start the u.s space force or maybe
uh invest more funds and resources into
it
so maybe this is a way of preparing the
public for it but maybe there is truth
to it so let's
wait for the declassified report and
let's
wait for what they reveal in it and then
we will have more information
as a scientist you need data and only
then you can uh
you can pass any uh
only then can you come come to sort of a
conclusion so as you will see right now
scientists are rather quiet about this
they are waiting for more data
so let's let's wait for more data
okay there is
one second
okay pankaj sharma thank you sir the
question is
can isro make money through asteroid
mining if yes
then how much would it cost and how much
profit will it make
do you think isro is underfunded
excellent question this is about the
indian space program and the indian
space agency isro
so let me give you some broad statistics
in this year 2021 till date
the chinese space program has made about
15 rocket launches
and it's mostly been record
reconnaissance satellites which is spy
satellites
military satellites so their space
program is very active
today is the is the sixth uh today is
the fifth
of june that's we are like almost
halfway through the year
so in about half a year they have made
15 rocket launches
now take space x which is a private
company
they have made 16 launches of the falcon
9 and the falcon heavy rocket
and they have made four experimental
launches of their starship rocket
so they are very active in in launching
vehicles and also testing this new
rocket the starship
on the other hand isro in this year has
made one
launch of the pslv and that's it
so india's space program is
kind of dormant it is it's half a week
half asleep
not much activity going on absolutely no
new tests are happening for new
technologies new rockets heavier more
powerful rockets
absolutely nothing so
as a scientist the isro has great
scientists by the way
some of the best scientists in the world
they have done so much with so little
money
so as a scientist you want to test every
day
right that's the nature of science and
technology you cannot progress without
testing new technology you have ideas
you have concepts you
you will create models and prototypes
and then you want to test these models
and prototypes
to see how well or how badly they
perform
and then you iteratively progress and
and make it better
so that is the whole concept of testing
not only rockets it so it also applies
to software and to all kinds of
other technologies so why is israel not
launching rockets or rockets why is it
not testing new rockets
because it is grossly underfunded it's
as simple as that
we have the talent we have the best
brains in the world
we have the best scientists in isro they
have achieved so much but the only
thing that is holding israel back is the
lack of vision and lack of ambition of
our
political class they are not funding
israel enough
i mean we know that isro center sent a
spacecraft to mars right a few years ago
it was the mangalyan one mission
the budget for this mission was was less
than the budget for the hollywood movie
gravity
so this mission succeeded in sending a
spacecraft
to another planet in the first attempt
successfully
on less money it takes to make a
hollywood movie
i mean that's the kind of funding or
lack of it that isro receives and yet it
does so well
so yes isro is grossly underfunded
uh about making money through asteroid
mining we have to first reach the
asteroids
and then we will be able to mine the
asteroids right we don't have even have
a space program
a manned space program yet the ghanaian
mission was supposed to launch
in 2122 i think it has been delayed
because of the current situation which
we are aware of
so it has been pushed back if i am if i
am
correctly informed so we need to first
have a
a manned space program we need to be
able to launch human beings into
low earth orbit and then we need to be
able to progress
beyond low earth orbit up to the moon
for example
and only then can we think about going
further
so the asteroid belt is between mars and
jupiter
so we have to first be able to reach
mars
and only then can we go further ahead
from mars so it's a long
road we haven't even taken the first
step yet
in even putting human beings into low
earth orbit
so we have a long road ahead of us as
far as isro is concerned
i sincerely hope that the indian
government will invest
in space exploration and india's
indigenous space program
because that is what holds the key to
the future of india to a great extent
because
the two or three countries that are
going to lead the world in space
exploration in the 21st centuries
are the two or three countries who will
decide the fate of the entire planet
that's how simple it is so india has to
take the lead
right now india is doing nothing which
is disappointing but i hope that there
will be a change soon
so i hope that answers your question
pankaj thank you for the question
okay let's take some more questions
this is from anurag shekhar thank you
anurag
appreciate it uh
thank you very much for starting this
series you are one of the few people
preserving our national treasures thank
you so much you don't have a question
uh i appreciate your kind uh remark
i really thank you for that thank you so
much i'm i'm happy to interact with you
guys it's uh
it's it's great fun and it's it's really
nice to see so much interest
in these topics which are not
essentially part of the mainstream
conversation
the mainstream conversation is politics
in bollywood and the
breaking news what i talk about is
something very different from that so i
am very
glad to see so much participation from
you guys so
so thank you appreciate it
okay one more question
this is from akshat bhadwaj thank you
akshat
how is the chinese space program as
compared to israel
so the chinese program is far ahead of
isro
at the moment it is a very active
program they have a
they have an entire family of rockets
and these some of these rockets are
quite powerful they can lift very heavy
payloads
into low earth and geostationary orbits
uh so they have been testing this for a
very long time they they are a very
ambitious nation the chinese communist
party is very ambitious and they have
placed a great deal of emphasis on
science and technology
since the days of mao zedong since the
1960s
so the chinese acquired rocket
technology from the russians
it was i think the chinese uh acquired
technology in the form of the r2
semyorka rocket
if i if my memory serves me right
so this was the russian version of a
rocket that the nazis had developed
during the second world war
it was a russian improvement upon the v2
missile that the nazis had developed
so this is the rockets that the soviets
had developed and they were improving
upon
and they transferred some of this
technology to the chinese and the
chinese have
iteratively built upon that over the
years and the decades and today they
have very powerful rockets
so it's all thanks to this initial
transfer of technology
from russia so the chinese space program
is
more ambitious it is more structured it
is better funded
than anything isro has if israel gets
the kind of funding that they get
india will overtake china very quickly
but
india is not investing in israel india
doesn't have
at the moment the kind of ambition that
i would like to see
so that's your answer in short the
chinese program space program is far
ahead of israel
at the moment in terms of capabilities
not in terms of talent
in terms of capabilities and funds
and resources and infrastructure
okay next question
okay again by anurag uh thank you nurag
there are concepts of vimanas mentioned
in ancient
texts like the ramayana pushpak viman
and also
highly advanced weapons like brahmastra
what are your views on this
and why all these concepts vanished
good question so yes we have had this
concept of vimanas of
flying uh of flying vehicles
for thousands of years our ancient texts
like the ramayana speak about vimanas
and like you say like you have stated
here we have this
we have these ancient concepts of very
powerful
energetic weapons like the burmastra
which
sound like the present-day nuclear
weapons so
i do not know what this technology
involved what is
was it real technology or was it
something we had imagined
i do not know i would need some sort of
hard evidence to to arrive at some sort
of conclusion
but i am not one of the people who said
this is nonsense
if you talk to 99 of scientists if you
talk to scientists
99 of them will say this is all nonsense
it is all mythology
and we need to get to move forward and
stop believing in all this nonsense
that's what they will say i say we need
to have an open mind india was a highly
developed civilization
it was the most scientifically advanced
civilization of all time
and especially of the ancient times its
science and technology was
leaps and bounds ahead of every other
civilization and culture on the planet
and we have evidence of that we have the
harappan era which was architecturally
incredible
we had immense feats of engineering
precision engineering
hydro engineering we had we had
naval capabilities and it actually seems
like we
understood we had calculated in the
harappan days
the actual speed of light and we had a
very great amount of
astronomical knowledge as well very
accurate astronomical knowledge
there is this uh a stone carving has
been
excavated has been discovered in kashmir
okay in the kashmir valley
which depicts two suns in the sky
and there are some uh constellation
figures around that
so this looked like some imagination of
some ancient artists who has put two
suns in the sky
but then scientists at tifr the tata
institute of fundamental research
actually went through the ancient
astronomical data
and they found that there was a
supernova in the fifth or sixth century
bce or thereabouts
which occurred exactly where this second
sun was
was shown in this carving so this is the
oldest and earliest depiction of a
supernova in human history
so that's how advanced we were we were
we were keeping
track of celestial events and our
science and technology was very advanced
so do we have evidence of poshmark
or other vimanas or the brahmastra as of
today we did not have it
but we know that we have lost all our
ancient records of our history
they were all burned during the uh
turkic invasions and the
complete destruction of all of our all
our universes and libraries
so we have lost our data all our records
so we cannot
just dismiss these uh these records of
these
vimanas and advanced weapons it is
possible we may have had some technology
like that
but to definitively
make some sort of comment on that i
would need to see
evidence so i hope that we look for
evidence we do some archaeological work
which we are not doing it at the moment
and hopefully we will be able to throw
more light upon this matter
so good question thank you
kikali chishi thank you so much thank
you appreciate it
a question by pragya kapoor the indian
government is is funding israel more
than ever
but the indian budget don't allow us to
invest more but
even then government is fun increasing
its funding every year
how can india balance its budget well i
am not
an economist but there are always
many ways of cutting out wasteful
expenditure
every government has wastage of
there are schemes that are populist in
nature
they are designed to appease certain
sections of society
or certain classes of society etc
certain schemes are good for garnering
votes but they are not good for the
nation in the long run
so i am not making any specific
criticisms or pointing out any specific
schemes
i am just saying that it is always
possible to for
a country as large and as immense as
india to better allocate its financial
and budgetary resources
in the things that really matter in the
long run
so we may if we invest money in science
and technology
and space programs at the present time
it may look like we are wasting money
but 30 years down the line it's going to
pay back
10 times more than we ever expected
because technology
always comes back in in different forms
so the u.s space program
was basically a military competition
with russia
and yet the technology that that were
that had to be invented
to make the space program possible had
in
immense uh spin-off effects
in in the civilian population i mean so
many technologies came out of the space
program
which were initially meant to be
military technologies
but then they became available for
civilian use and that advanced the
economy and the standards of living
there are so many such technologies
wireless communication
is is one of these and uh i don't have
it at the
at my fingertips right now but there are
a lot of technology that came out of
this
and these are all more or less
ubiquitous today
in in our day-to-day lives for example
we would not be having this conversation
without space technology
right and much more so
that's why we need to invest in this we
can better balance our budgets and we
can
we can maybe cut cut down on some
expenditures and
invest in something that would be good
for the country in the long term
so you always should keep the long term
in mind
temporary pleasures may make you happy
for the next five minutes but it may
have a harmful effect
in the long run so always think of the
long run always think of the next
generations the future generations
and the long-term future and prosperity
of the country so i would want
the government to fund israel more
thank you for the question
next question legal freedom thank you
thank you very much
uh there is a series called ancient
aliens and they are showing our gods
like aliens
is earth a space lab for aliens so i
have not really
watched this series maybe an episode or
two
at most i am aware that they kind of
depict
india's gods like uh aliens
like extraterrestrial beings
i think there is a very erroneous and
somewhat disrespectful depiction
of india's gods and india's india's
culture
they are seeing they are trying to see
everything through a very
particular very specific lens so if you
have if the only tool you have is a
hammer
then every problem looks like a nail so
that's the kind of approach they're
taking everything is aliens everything
is extraterrestrials
all ancient technology was it was
possible because extraterrestrials
gifted it to us not because we
are intelligent enough to develop it so
i
i personally do not uh put too much
credence into
some of the conclusions they are drawing
especially about india's ancient gods
maybe some of the other facts that that
they are bringing out may be
valuable and valid i don't know but the
part about indian gods
i do not really agree with that i think
it's a little disrespectful
is the earth a space lab for aliens well
we don't have any evidence as of now we
don't have sufficient data to come to a
conclusion
i would like to see more data and then
we can comment about it so like uh
like the one of the previous commenters
said some information is going to be
declassified soon
in the united states so let's see what
it is and then we can
maybe come to a better kind of
understanding about what's happening
so thank you for the question
i hope i have not missed anything
thank you again uh what is my opinion on
space debris
space debris are a long term problem
it's an increasing problem it's going to
get worse
and it's going to have uh it's going to
cause problems in the future because
we are basically treating the low earth
orbit as
a cosmic junkyard we're just dumping
stuff there
and it's flying around and it's already
causing problems for the international
space station
they have impacts from space debris
small space debris from time to time
and they have learned how to deal with
these impacts
but i hope such a thing doesn't happen
but
one of these days something bigger might
impact the international space station
or some other satellite
and it could cause uh
you know some kind of harm to human life
and if it impacts the satellite and the
satellite disintegrates then it's to
cause an explosion
of space debris which could have a kind
of domino effect and
start destroying more and more
satellites so this is a very real
possibility
and i think that every nation that is
capable of achieving low earth orbit
especially commercially should be
very responsible in the way it this
disposes
of defunct satellites there should be a
proper protocol of of
re-entering the satellite into the
atmosphere and burning it into that in
the atmosphere
because of the friction that it will
encounter
satellites should not be left to just
drift in
low earth orbit and other space junction
junk should also not be
left behind so there needs to be a
proper
protocol for dealing with this so space
debris definitely is a big problem
and i hope we take better care of this
issue
so good question thank you for the
question
okay this is from abhishek srivastav
isn't it doubtful that thank you
abhishek
isn't it doubtful that harapan
civilization is too advanced
is it possible that aliens may have
contacted them
is it possible that aliens had contacted
them it is possible
we don't have proof that aliens did not
contact them
we don't have proof they did not it did
not happen we also don't have proof that
aliens contacted them so as of now
with the lack of evidence that we have
we cannot
pass judgment one way or the other it is
possible that aliens may have contacted
them
is the harappan civilization too
advanced well it looks like it's a
really advanced because it's a vast
immense urban civilization like
multiple times as large as egypt it is
larger than egypt and mesopotamia
put together it is still larger than
that it's it's the
it was immense and that's only the part
that we have excavated
it may be even larger than that i think
it's quite likely
that the whole of india was urbanized
in that manner so yes it was incredibly
advanced for the time and the kind of
engineering
we had the kind of science and
technology we had in that era was
mind-boggling so is it possible that
aliens gave us this technology well i
don't have proof that it
did not give us technology but i think
it's also very possible that we were
intelligent enough
to develop this technology and this
all these capabilities over thousands of
years
because as you know our civilization has
been proven
to be at least 10 000 years years old
from the archaeological record
so it's possible also that we may have
developed this technology on our own
so this question is essentially
well it is it is to be continued it is
to be resolved with more evidence in the
future
but my strong conviction is that we
developed all these capabilities
on our own because of the advanced
nature of our civilization
so thank you for the question
okay some more questions
this is by
let me come back to this thank you
randeep appreciate it
thank you chetan
and thank you bhargava thank you very
much appreciate it
okay i will come back to that question
again this is by chandan
mohanta according to uh thank you
chandan according to dr steven greer
we can contact et's via ce5
my opinion i have connected them via ce5
can you please try and make people aware
if you're successful no harm in
trying unfortunately i don't know what
ce5 is let me just
google it briefly ce5 what is that
ce5
[Music]
ce5 handbook
okay so you're talking about the ce5
handbook an easy to use guide to help
you contact extraterrestrial life
interesting so i was not aware of this
specific handbook i will look it up
i don't know what it is so sure i i
appreciate your suggestion i will i will
take a look at this and see and see what
uh i can make of it so
thank you for the question
okay back to char govinda thank you very
much
can you explain about why we did not
become the leading nation before the
invasions
if everything we did was more advanced
then where did we fail
yes yes excellent question so
what is the meaning of the leading
nation we were a civilization
and we were the leading civilization the
most advanced civilization
so we had these cycles of history our
history has
was cyclical in nature there were times
when we were united under one
single emperor for example chandragupta
maurya
for example kanishka the kushan
for example the gupta empire
and so on so we had cycles of time when
we were unified
under one single emperor and there were
times when we had mahajanapadas and
various kingdoms
so we were disunited politically but we
were still one single culture and
civilization
and we were scientifically and
technologically the most advanced
we we had the highest gdp of any
geographical area
in the history of the world so we were
the most advanced civilization
we were the leading civilization before
the invasions
everything was more advanced so where
did we did we fail
we became too civilized and too peaceful
right so i have said this before in a
different
forum on ranveer's channel that
there is a piece of ancient piece of
wisdom that when you meet a swordsman
draw your sword do not recite poetry to
somebody who is not a poet
and it seems that we may have
kind of forgotten this particular piece
of wisdom
so when the turkic and other invasions
happened we kind of treated them as if
they were as civilized as us
they were their intent the intent of the
invaders
was to slaughter us and wipe out our
civilization
and our some of our kings treated them
as if they were civilized
and they could be dealt with in a
civilized manner
and the other thing was that we were not
united politically so
this these invasions happened at a time
when india was not unified
under a single emperor if it had been
that way
then nobody would have been able to
invade us for example people like
alexander tried to invade india the
great conqueror alexander
he failed miserably because india was
unified under
emperor chandragupta maurya so whenever
india has been unified
and unified not just under one emperor
but unified as a people
at those times nobody has been able to
successfully invade us
so these invasions caught us at the
wrong time
we were too civilized there is no point
having great
culture great architecture and great art
if you can't defend it what is the point
of creating great art great architecture
great culture
if you do not have the willingness or
the wherewithal
to defend it so that is the lessons of
history that we need to learn
so that's an excellent question thank
you
okay let me
take some more questions
this is by naveen eka thank you so much
thank you very much
uh as confirmed by obama on ufo and
according to bob lazar's documentary
the u.s have a crashed ufo and the ufo
moves in atmosphere by squeezing
space-time through gravity-generating
reactors
is such a thing possible so i am aware
of the fact that
the former president obama has made some
sort of disclosure that ufos may exist
or something like that
and that the us government and the
pentagon has some
crashed alien artifacts of some kind
no details have been forthcoming but
some
vague disclosure has been made
so the speculation is that these are
very advanced technologies
these alien spacecraft travel
faster than possible the speed of light
they use
the warping of space time
through technology that doesn't exist
yet in our
in our basically uh knowledge
and we don't have the capability to do
that but yes according to certain
uh certain solutions of einstein's
equations of general relativity it may
be possible
to build a motor that can actually
warp space time in a manner that you can
travel
faster than the speed of light it may be
possible
uh new new research papers have very
recently been published
that suggest that this technology may be
possible
if we have sufficient power but the
power needed to do this is
incredibly immense you may need to
basically harness
black holes you may need to be able to
control black holes and use them to
generate the kind of power
that is needed to to power such an
engine
so theoretically it looks like in the
future such
technologies may be possible and other
civilizations that are
way more advanced than ours may be able
to do this
so the possibility does exist do we have
any confirmation that such ufos are
there
we don't have confirmed evidence we have
some leaked
videos black and white videos that don't
really prove anything
so we are still waiting for more
evidence as i have said before
i am i am not somebody who dismisses the
claims
of ufos that ufos exist but i would like
to see
evidence hard evidence multi-source
evidence
before i can come to some sort of a
proper conclusion
so we are still waiting for that but
yeah i agree that obama has made some
sort of
statement about this so let's wait and
watch
good question thank you
okay this is by revant thank you any
book suggestions on this topic
project circle so uh i am assuming
you're talking about ufos i don't know
any books about ufos because
i have i have not been reading up about
ufos
when i was a child like seven eight nine
ten years old i read a lot about ufos
but those were the books that children
read right
so as i grew older i kind of uh
moved away from exploring the topic of
ufos because i realized that there is
not sufficient data about this it's all
mostly
speculation and conjecture and unproven
claims
so i unfortunately do not know any good
books about this topic
uh i will look it up and maybe the next
time
we discuss this topic i can give some
book suggestions but as of now
unfortunately i do not have any
so uh apologies for that and and thank
you for the question
okay let's see some more
this is by caffeinated caffeine king
thank you did the u.s really send a man
to the moon successfully or is it just a
fabrication
so yeah interesting i am aware of the
claims that this was all a hoax that the
moon landings were faked so yeah there
have been
significant claims to this effect
some people believe that these are all
faked moon landings
so here's my position about this we know
that the americans
created this space agency called nasa
we know that they invested immense
amounts of money
into this organization in the 1960s they
were investing like three to four
percent of the national budget
into this organization nasa and it was
used to create this enormous
infrastructure
thousands of scientists were hired
office buildings were created enormous
labs were created
lots of research was done all of this
research was compiled and documented in
thousands and thousands of
pages of documentation rockets were
built we have seen the rockets people
have witnessed these
rocket launches thousands of people at
one time have witnessed every
rocket launch many rockets crashed
eventually they improved upon the
rockets and we know that these rockets
went up into the atmosphere we know that
they were carrying people
so is it possible to do all this and yet
try to fake a moon landing
with after investing billions of dollars
worth of funds in creating all this
infrastructure
we know that this saturn 5 rocket did go
up into the atmosphere
we know that it was launched and after
spending so much money
constructing this enormously powerful
rocket that actually works
i mean why would you just not go to the
moon
so so my position is that i completely
believe that
the moon landings happened we know that
the
us invested so much in building all this
technology and capabilities
so they might as well use it to actually
go to the moon
so i am pretty certain that the moon
landings did happen it's not a
fabrication
at least in my opinion if somebody
disagrees i respect your opinion but
my opinion is that it did happen and we
have seen evidence of that
because uh our chandrayaan-1
orbiter i think it i believe it
took images of the of one of the apollo
landing sites
and you could actually make out the
apollo lander and and some footprints
and all that
from the chandrayaan photographs so
clearly
there is evidence and independently
verifiable evidence not american
photographs but indian photographs so i
am pretty much
certain that this actually did happen
but good question it's good to discuss
these topics
and and these claims so thank you
all right some more questions
pragna krishna thank you so much thank
you appreciate it
this is by rohit raina thank you thank
you rohit
uh thank you for this i would like to
would love to interact for my sci-fi
novel
question one is god real if if yes then
in which dimension he lives
are there 11 dimensions as per our vedas
two are there gravitational anomalies
thank you rohit uh is god real well
i wish i knew i wish i knew
i would love to have a real god i i
hope that there is a god a good
benevolent god
as as we all as many people believe in
i do not have an answer to whether god
is real because i have
seen with my limited senses and my
limited intellect i have not seen
i have not been successful in perceiving
any direct physical evidence of god
it is most likely because of my limited
senses and my limited intellect
okay so is it possible that god exists
i think it is very possible that god
exists but i unfortunately
and regrettably hadn't have not seen any
evidence so it is only because of my
shortcomings and not because god may not
exist
so personally i have not seen evidence
but i am very hopeful that god does
exist
are there 11 questions as per our vedas
well according to the vedas i don't know
how many dimensions are there but
according to string theory
there could be 10 or 11 dimensions we
have not seen any
evidence of these dimensions but
mathematically
string theory doesn't work the theory
doesn't hold together
unless we introduce 10 dimensions but
we have never seen any actual evidence
of these dimensions in
in the physical world so it is
speculated that these dimensions are
curled up and compactified in a variety
of ways
but this is all theory string theory
has not made a single prediction that is
actually observable or verifiable or
falsifiable
thus far so once again we don't know the
answer you see
science has a lot of theories but there
are a lot of theories that have
and there are a lot of things that have
no answers so that's where we are right
now our
actual knowledge we might think it is
immense but it's actually very limited
so so that's the answer to the
dimensions question
and are there any gravitational
anomalies so i'm not sure what is the
definition of
definition of normally i would imagine
what you're trying to say
is the mathematical singularities that
lie at the heart of black holes
so it is possible that these uh
singularities may actually be something
else see
what i'm talking about is that in the
theory of general relativity
there are solutions of einstein's
equations
where space-time the curvature of
space-time and the density of matter
becomes
infinite so when something goes to
infinity it's called a mathematical
singularity
now what does this mean in the physical
world because all this mathematics needs
to have some meaning
in the physical world for a physics
theory to be valid
so according to so when something blows
up when you have a division by zero and
you have
an infinity it actually means that your
theory has a hole in it it doesn't mean
that space time actually becomes
infinite in curvature it doesn't mean
that matter actually becomes infinitely
dense
what this singularity indicates is that
the theory of general relativity has a
flaw in it
it has there is a loophole there is a
hole in it
and that probably is the fact that it it
does we don't know how it works
at the ultra microscopic quantum level
so the thing is that we don't have a
quantum theory of gravity
when we try to when we try to marry
general relativity with quantum physics
it just blows up it fails we are unable
to
uh create a theory of
curve space time at the ultra
microscopic level
we have been trying to do it for decades
we are still
failing so that is one of the big
unanswered
and open questions in physics so this
gravitational singularity the
singularity of space-time could be the
anomaly that you're referring to
i don't think they actually exist but
what actually is there
inside a black hole that is not known to
us at all
so a gravitational anomaly could be a
black hole or it could be
the hypothetical wormhole or white hole
do they exist we don't know yet we know
that something that looks like black
holes does exist
we know that there are ultra compact
black
dark objects at the center of black
holes
at the center of galaxies these are
supermassive black holes
and there are other black holes as well
so yeah these do exist but
the other anomalies like white holes and
wormholes
we have never observed them thus far so
good question thank you
let me go ahead
okay this is a question by rajna singh
thank you rajna
can you explain time as a dimension well
time is one of the other
great mysteries of physics we don't
really know what it is
we i mean in the in the theory of
general relativity we take time as the
fourth dimension
so we see the world as something that is
three dimensional
in nature length breadth and height
the three dimensions of of space
and this theory the general theory of
relativity
considers time to be the fourth
dimension
so that is how relativity looks at time
as the fourth dimension
but we do not understand the nature of
time we don't know what it is it's one
of the great mysteries
is time an emergent phenomenon is it
something that
emerges from the nature of space time
and the nature of the universe
or is it something that is inherent to
the unit to the universe
we don't know that could time be
continuous could it be discontinuous
is time quantum in nature do we have
atoms and molecules of time so these
are open questions and we don't have the
least
idea of what time is we have a very
vague
understanding of time we don't even have
a proper definition of time
it could be something that may possibly
emerge out of the
second law of thermodynamics it may be
related to the quantity that is called
entropy
which is a measure of disorder it could
possibly
be a manifestation of the
decoherence that happens at the quantum
level
and so on so there are many theories
none of these theories has been proven
so time is one of the great open
mysteries
of nature and in physics so imagine that
we don't even know what time is
so there's a lot to explore in the world
and we still haven't
got things figured out so great question
thank you rajna
okay let me see some more questions
the anonymous vlogger thank you
is it true about chandratal lake and
aliens
ah i am sorry i don't have an answer to
your question i don't know
the chandratal lake i think it could be
in the himalayas if i'm
not mistaken i only have a vague
memory of of hearing this name but i'm
sorry i don't have an answer to this
i will look it up and maybe the next
time we have this conversation this this
discussion
i could update you about that but as of
now i don't know about that
so apologies for that
anurag shekhar thank you so much can you
please explain about wormholes according
to your perspective
so so
so the the black holes as you know are
the result of these some of the
solutions to einstein's equations
and other solutions of einstein's
equations
give the concept of wormholes so
wormhole is essentially
a tunnel that connects two disparate
regions of space-time
so the universe is made up of something
called space-time
a four dimensional fabric of space time
three spatial dimensions
and one temporal dimension and these
four dimensions work together as a
single fabric
it is the stage upon which the universe
exists so that is space time so you can
look up on space time as a sheet
i mean this is very commonly known that
you can look up on space time is a sheet
of fabric
and the presence of mass like a ball
would make a
a kind of a dent or or some kind of
curvature in the space-time
fabric and that is what causes the force
that we know
as gravity that is what we perceive as
the force of gravity
so if you could connect two different
regions of space-time
by go by by making a hole through it
that would be a wormhole
so that is our wall in very simple terms
it is
a connection between two far-off regions
of space-time it's like taking a
shortcut
and our wormholes possible well
according to the einstein according to
certain solutions of
the einstein equations yes wormholes may
be possible but it's not possible
to keep these wormholes open unless you
have some sort of special
special exotic matter in there
essentially you would need to insert a
negative mass
inside of a mole in order to keep it
open because wormholes tend to close
they the natural tendency of these
theoretical wormholes
is to close off very quickly and they
would close off pinch off
and become two black holes so to keep
this connection
to keep the tunnel open you would have
to insert something
which has a negative mass inside of it
and as you know
we have never seen any evidence of
negative mass in
well in our entire human history so
positive mass
it falls downwards negative mass would
be repulsive in nature so it would go
upwards
that's the kind of exotic matter we're
talking about
the other possibility is that something
called cosmic strings
which possibly were formed in the very
initial moments after the big bang if
these cosmic strings exist
then maybe they could thread wormholes
and keep these wormholes open
so that is a possibility but there is no
evidence of it
thus far so do wormholes exist we have
never seen any but
hypothetically theoretically they are
possible
so it may be something that could form
the basis of
future technologies when we are more
advanced than we
we are right now so that hopefully
answers your question
thank you for the question
okay this is from abhishek shivastav
thank you abhishek
where did the indus valley civilization
disappear
and all scripts of that era have been
deciphered
well what happened to the indus valley
civilization and its people
so those people are right here we are
the descendants of the indus valley
people
we are the descendants of the harappan
people this civilization never
disappeared
what happened was that there was climate
change which made habitation around the
saraswati river
unfeasible so six thousand
actually eight thousand years ago the
indian monsoon was
much heavier than what it is today
at around 6000 bce the indian monsoon
started
declining monotonically slowly slowly
slowly
over centuries because of climate change
and the great river saraswati was fed by
the indian monsoon
so it was a great river it was a mighty
river and it was entirely fed by the
indian monsoon
and it emerged from the himalayas
through glacial melt water
but the bulk of this reverse water came
from the indian monsoon and other
streams and all that
so as the monsoon declined this river
started drying out
and about three and a half thousand
years ago it dried out and stopped
reaching the sea so because of this
climate change
and factors such as that these great
cities
and great urban settlements that had
been built around
the river banks of this great river
there are thousands of such settlements
that have not been explored
archaeologically so because this river
dried out
the lifestyle that they were enjoying
could no longer be sustained
and they had to slowly over many
centuries
gradually abandon these cities and move
elsewhere so these people moved
eastwards into the present-day regions
of madhya pradesh
even uttar pradesh and mostly madhya
pradesh rajasthan gujarat
some of them may have gone upwards to
punjab haryana and all that
so their descendants are us this
civilization has never died out
it endures right we are the
continuation of the so-called harappan
civilization
it is not some other civilization it is
our ancestors
so our history textbooks portrayed as
something that was different
some they portrayed something that got
over it ended
that is a lie it is a it is a distortion
of history
the civilization has never died out it
endures we have evidence of cultural
continuity
that is 10 000 years old and that begins
in the oldest settlement that is found
in the harappan era
so the civilization never disappeared
are
all scripts of that era deciphered no
the so-called harappan script is still
undeciphered
because very little effort has been put
into deciphering it
i hope that with the advent of
artificial intelligence and machine
learning technologies
we can start using those technologies to
decipher
this script i don't think it's very
difficult once you have enough manpower
enough resources and enough funding i
think it should be
not very hard to decipher the script but
somebody needs to get this together
to get the brains together to get the
technology in the right place and to
allocate the kind of funding that's
needed for this project
so i would imagine that the right person
to do that or the right
power to do this is the government of
india so far they have shown
no inclination for this hopefully in the
future they'll wake up
and take up this project so i hope that
answers your question thank you very
much abhishek
okay let me find some more questions
this is by vihanga korane thank you
vihang
is it really possible to explore a black
hole the way it was shown in the movie
interstellar
without getting disintegrated under the
influence of
gravity so that movie was pretty much
accurate it's possible to skirt outs a
skirt
around a black hole and
use it for a gravity for a gravitational
assist
as long as you don't come too close and
as long as you don't
cross or even touch the event horizon
because the event horizon is the point
of no return
once you are there you're done so if you
have enough velocity if you have escape
velocity
for that particular black hole then you
can take a hyperbolic
trajectory and shoot past it and use it
for a gravitational assist
so the the physics is pretty
straightforward actually
what would happen is as you come closer
to the to the black hole
you will experience time dilation which
means that
time will slow down for you from your
perspective so what
seems to be a minute for you could be
very much
longer for somebody who is far away from
that massive black hole
so all these effects have been shown
pretty accurately in that movie
interstellar
i was very impressed with the way the
the entire physics
was portrayed i think they hired some
physicists as consultants
to get the to get all of this right so
it is possible
theoretically to do that but
we don't know any black hole in our
vicinity thankfully
where we could go and do these
experiments so maybe
our descendants in the future could do
these things
but yes the the physics in that movie
was pretty much spot on
so good question
okay this is by mother of dubai thank
you mother
what is the artificial sun that china is
making i think china is
trying to attempting to construct a
fusion reactor
so when we look at the sun i would not
advocate looking at it directly because
it will harm your eyes but
the sun is a massive
nuclear fusion reactor so what we
witness when we see the sunlight
is we are witnessing the light that
comes out of a
massive thermonuclear fusion reaction
so we all have seen a nuclear reaction
it's the sun
so what china is doing is they are
attempting to create to construct
a reactor that could achieve nuclear
fusion
so the nuclear reactors that are used
all over the world are
fission reactors they use
what is known as nuclear fission which
is the splitting of an atom to produce
energy is usually various isotopes of
uranium
and plutonium sometimes thorium that are
used for
conventional nuclear reactors now
what can be achieved in a fusion reactor
is that you take the
nuclear reaction which is the
thermonuclear fission
which is the fission reaction and use it
to compress
matter together and achieve fusion so
when you achieve
fusion of atoms it the output of energy
is much higher than what
you would get in a fission reaction so
that is the
so-called holy grail of nuclear physics
to achieve
fusion on earth as of now we don't have
the technology to achieve fusion
it's very difficult because of the
immense temperatures
and pressures that you would need to
achieve in order to spark
a fusion reaction so that is what china
is trying to do
it has not achieved it but that is the
ambition so that's the artificial sun
that you are talking about so good
question
okay
yogesh thank you very much appreciate it
does planet x exist beyond pluto it is
possible
uh the kind of gravitational uh
effects we are seeing and the kind of
orbits certain uh
certain protoplanetary bodies and
certain
minor planets etc etc etc are showing
over there
it does indicate that there could be a
massive planet out there
beyond the orbit of pluto so the data
that we have seems to indicate the
presence of a massive
object a massive planet there
but thus far we have not been able to
actually
find any evidence of it there is a
search going on as we speak
many astronomers and many uh departments
of astronomy are actively looking for
signs of such a planet so we don't know
if it is there or not but
it looks like something should be out
there it could even be a small black
hole
that could also do the same job that a
hidden planet would do so yeah there
could be something out there
we are looking for it at the moment
question by shashank thank you shashank
are we living in a simulation
uh it is a possibility i cannot discount
that
uh do we have any evidence that we are
living in a simulation we don't have
evidence but
as as our technology gets more powerful
we can see the kind of simulated
environments we can create
in for example gaming environments if
you
if you remember the playstation 2 which
came out about 20 years ago
the kind of graphics it had was very
rudimentary
today you have technologies like the
playstation 5 which have a very
realistic
environment that it can simulate so the
concept is that if you have a powerful
enough supercomputer
you can actually simulate an entire
universe with proper laws of physics
inside the cyberspace of this
super computer so you could actually
have intelligent life forming
within the simulation and that is the
concept of the simulation hypothesis
that we could be actually living inside
such a massive simulation
which is being run by some hyper
computer
which is owned by some very intelligent
species of of of beings
we don't have any evidence of it but the
possibility cannot be discounted so good
question
question by aditya aka good uh thank you
did shivkar bapuji talapade fly of imana
well that is what the claim is
we don't have evidence today of what
happened
there have been eyewitnesses who claim
that he did fly
a vimana he constructed a vimana using
the
instructions in the vyamanekshastra text
and he actually succeeded in flying one
of these machines
as of today we have either no evidence
of it or
the evidence has been lost so without
evidence
i have not seen the evidence so i cannot
say that he has actually done it
but i have not seen i mean there is no
proof that he has not done it
so he may have done it he may not have
done it we do not have evidence
today unfortunately so that's the answer
in short
thank you for the question
abhishek shivasta thank you can we
predict
that how the universe will end so
there are a number of um
a number of theories so according to big
bang cosmology
and according to the evidence and data
that we have
the universe is currently expanding and
the expansion
is actually accelerating so the universe
is expanding faster
and faster so distant stars and galaxies
are getting more and more distant from
us
we can see this because of the gravity
because of the
red shift that we observe in the spectra
that is uh detected from these galaxies
and stars
so we know that the expansion is
accelerating we can see the redshift
so it looks like from whatever evidence
we have
that the universe will keep on expanding
forever
and it will become cold and lifeless and
eventually all stars and galaxies will
will be too far away for us to see them
and eventually
even the fusion within stars will die
out and everything will become cold and
lifeless
so that is one possibility of how the
universe will end
but that's not the only possibility
maybe there will be a big crunch
so maybe at some point in time the
expansion will slow down stop
and reverse so it may contract again
and it may and the opposite of a big
bang may happen which is a big crunch
so that is another possibility the third
possibility is we may have
a cyclical universe so big bangs and big
crunches happening all
the time one after the other
simultaneous or not simultaneously
but in succession so that is the
cyclical cosmology
model so there are a number of
hypotheses
or theories but we don't have any proof
or evidence
this the science is still developing we
have lots of
uh unknowns right now so that is
the rudimentary analysis that we can do
as of today
so we don't really know what's going to
happen but we have
some theories and models so that's the
answer thank you
thank you thank you so much thank you
appreciate it thank you very much
okay again by abhishek thank you
abhishek if there is cultural continuity
from indus valley civilization
then we should have to be more advanced
than we are right now but why are we not
because we are not advanced the way we
should have been
because we lost our science and
technology
we lost our universities we lost our
libraries
and we lost the knowledge that had been
accumulated for thousands of years
so when these turkic invasions happened
about a thousand years ago
they stole all the important texts from
our libraries
text of mathematics of astronomy of
science
of ayurveda pharmacology and so many
more things
they took it to their country they
translated it into arabic
from the islamic world it made its way
into europe
and that's how europe got hold of
ancient indian mathematics and science
trigonometry in finite series calculus
and much more
and then the turkic invaders proceeded
to destroy our universities
they killed slaughtered all the gurus
all the students and the world burned
all the libraries
and that is how the knowledge that we
had acquired
over thousands of years was lost and
that is why
we became basically disconnected
from the knowledge that should have been
our heritage
and that is the reason why we are not
advanced
the way we should have been if this
calamity had not happened
if that if this calamity had not
happened then all the
technologies that have been developed in
the west would have been first invented
in india
the theories of quantum mechanics of
relativity and everything else
would most likely have been first
discovered in india
if all this had not happened so the
story the moral of the story is if you
have a great civilization you
should know how to protect it that is
the
moral of the story so thank you for the
question
thank you very much thank you
okay this is a question from indick
knowledge thank you
universe is expanding into what
what was before the big bang was it a
point-sized object
yeah okay that's the question what is
the universe expanding into is
the big question we don't know what it
is expanding into is there something
outside the universe
that it is expanding into well we cannot
answer the question
unless we can go outside our universe
and observe what is outside
but with the kind of technology and
knowledge that we have we cannot even
travel
outside our planet as of now we don't
even know how to reach the
the nearest planet which is venus or
mars
we can't even travel beyond our solar
system we can't travel beyond
our galaxy so the question of traveling
beyond our
universe and looking outside doesn't
exist right now
the question doesn't doesn't arise we
are not sufficiently advanced
as as a species to do that
so what is the universe expanding into
we don't know we do not have any
theory of what is outside of our
universe we do have
hypothesis the multiverse hypothesis so
there may be multiple universes out
there
beyond our own universe but it's a
hypothesis there is no proof of it
and it's not falsifiable so it's not a
really a valid scientific theory it's
just a hypothesis
what was before the big bang was it a
point size object so that's what the
big bang theory says that in the
beginning the universe was a
point-sized object of infinite density
of infinite energy
and it expanded into what we see it as
the
as the universe today so that is what we
understand
from the big bang theory that the uni
universe was a point-sized
zero-dimensional infinitely
dense object so that's the answer to
your question thank you
a question from richard nair is the
theory about the supermassive black hole
in our galaxy
actually being a fluff ball of darkness
true
it's a theory we have not
gone there and tested it because it's
too far
so there are many models for what a
black hole could actually be
maybe it's not even a black hole maybe
it's something else maybe it's a
fuzzball
maybe it's it's a ball of strings of of
one-dimensional strings
maybe it's a fluff ball of nose
maybe it's it's something else
maybe it's an eternally collapsing
object maybe it's not a true black hole
and some it's actually something that's
slightly larger than a black hole
so we don't really know what a black
hole actually is
is it really a black hole or is it
something else there are a number of
theories
the currently accepted consensus
is that black holes are actually the
black holes that
emerge out of the uh einstein equations
out of solutions of instance equations
in general relativity
but until we have a black hole in a
laboratory and we can test
it it's only a theory it may not
necessarily
turn out to be the way we think it is so
this theory is a valid theory but we
don't have any proof that can either
prove it
or or debunk it so it's a valid
scientific theory that's all i can say
at the present time so thank you for the
question
okay one second
kritanam koshik we follow your content
religiously please put out more
thank you very much thank you i shall
continue
having these sessions regularly thank
you very much
bubbly banerjee thank you bubbly
recommend the books to learn particle
physics entirely
so i think i have a video on my channel
in which i have given a number of book
recommendations about
physics uh it's not entirely about
particle physics i think it's about dark
matter dark energy and astrophysics
and the like but yes the books that i
have specified in that
will help you to some extent in
understanding
the concepts of particle physics as well
and maybe in the future i can do another
video in which i can
recommend a set of books in which which
could help you to learn particle physics
or other aspects of physics
so i would recommend that you check out
that video in my channel
thank you
legal freedom thank you elon musk
musk wants to colonize mars and bezos
wants the moon
what will happen if they are successful
are we going to see star wars in the
future so what's happening
is the initial stage of the
privatization
of space that is what's happening
and the us government is actually
funding some of these
space programs those of elon musk
and of bezos elon musk has this company
called spacex
and jeff bezos has a company called blue
origin
so jeff bezos is not is not
demonstrating as much
overt ambition as elon musk he says that
his ambition is to first
take the initial step and go to the moon
so he is doing it in a very
progressive gradual and step-by-step
manner
whereas elon musk is talking about going
to mars straight away
so they both are doing a great deal of
progress
they have invested a lot of money into
this they are doing a lot of tests
and they have actually built the rockets
that are capable already
of going this distance these rockets are
being tested a lot of testing is
necessary before you can put human
beings on these dockets
because human human lives are at stake
but
they will eventually be successful
once you pour sufficient money and funds
and resources into a program
and you have the basics of rocket flight
which
have already been validated for many
decades so it's going to succeed
eventually
so once it succeeds you're gonna see the
privatization of space
and yeah you're gonna have competition
and rivalries and some sort of star wars
maybe not actual kinetic warfare but yes
corporate warfare
and various kinds of rivalries so
if spacex is able to colonize mars in
the future they could claim
ownership of mars who knows that could
also happen
so all kinds of possibilities are open
right now the space race is
just beginning it's going to heat up
very soon
there's going to be a big rush to the
moon in this decade itself
and even to mars so i hope like i've
said before that india
will participate seriously and not just
participate but try to win the race
so that will make things really
interesting and it will be beneficial
for the future of humanity if a
non-american power would also
participate in the spacex in the space
race china is definitely
participating so is russia so is the the
european space agency so india should
also be very serious about this
so the future of space exploration is up
for grabs
as we speak right now thank you for the
question
this question is from randeep pradhan
thank you
are we heading towards a type 1
civilization
if yes then when when and do you think
there is life after death
sorry so the type one civilization on
the kardashev
scale is a civilization that is able to
control
and harness all the energy and resources
of its home planet so it means that this
civilization should be able to control
the weather it should be able to control
the oceans
it should be able to control all the
energy output that is
potentially available on the planet all
the natural gas all the petroleum
all the volcanic energy all the wind
energy all the thermal energy everything
so as of now we are very far away from
being a type one civilization
we are not heading towards it we are
actually
messing up our planet we are making it
difficult
to for for our uh descendants
and future generations to have a good
life on this planet
and so so we are quite far from being a
type 1 civilization
will we achieve it in the future i
as of now i think it's quite difficult
we need to really
turn our ways around and become more
efficient
and less wasteful in in the way we
uh carry out our day-to-day lives
especially the west which is this
this culture of disposability everything
is disposable
in the west use something once and throw
it so that is the kind of thing that is
destroying our planet and
that is one of the things and one of the
world views that is preventing us from
progressing in the direction of becoming
a type one civilization
so we would have to become more
efficient and more
uh and we would need to
treat nature and our resources with more
respect and stop treating earth as
a dust bin and then only we can think of
trying to move in the direction so
that's the answer
um do i think there is life after death
i i have no idea honestly i don't know
is there life after that is there
consciousness after the after death
the living body definitely dies decays
right
but does consciousness persist in some
form after death
that is the big question
um according to the many worlds theory
of
of quantum mechanics there is something
called
there's a thought experiment called
quantum suicide
i would suggest you guys read up about
that
so that kind of suggests that there
could be quantum immortality
and maybe consciousness could persist
after the physical body dies
that is one of the possibilities that
emerges out of the theory of quantum
mechanics
out of one of the interpretations of
quantum mechanics
so who knows we as of now we don't
really understand quantum mechanics at
all
we understand how to use it but we don't
understand what what it is telling us
maybe there are missing pieces of
information missing pieces of
the puzzle maybe we aren't intelligent
enough to
reach the correct level of understanding
so as of now we do not have answers to
that question
is there life after death and does
consciousness persist after death we
don't know as of now
but good question
okay let me take a couple more questions
it's a question by viraj money
my opinion on the theory that every
matter is a particle in consciousness
and acts as energy in in consciousness
so i think there is a theory called
pan psychism which says that
every which says that all matter
is imbued with some form or some degree
of consciousness
this is a theory in philosophy it's not
a scientific theory
it's a philosophical theory so there is
a clear distinction between philosophy
and science
science is a subset of philosophy and
philosophy is something that is beyond
science it is larger than science
so science essentially deals with the
observable universe and
physical objects philosophy also deals
with the physically
the observable universe and and physical
objects
but philosophy also deals with
non-physical objects
and ideas so the question of pan
psychism whether there is consciousness
in
inanimate objects and other matter
well that's a philosophical theory it is
a theory that has been around for a very
long time i believe that even
indian philosophy has this theory so
do we have scientific evidence of this
we do not have scientific evidence of
this
maybe our science hasn't progressed that
much maybe we aren't
we haven't achieved that level of
advancement to be able to test this
theory
so as of now there is no evidence of
this but
in the future we may be able to test
this out so
that is a brief answer to your question
thank you viraj
this is by soham barambe thank you soham
what do i think of the collision between
andromeda and milky way and can i
explain what small changes will occur
so good question the andromeda galaxy is
the farthest object that we can see with
the naked eye
it is our neighboring galaxy it is part
of the local
corner of the universe the local cluster
and
the milky way galaxy and andromeda
galaxy are
coming closer together every minute
every second
and eventually they're going to merge
they're going to combine it's not going
to be a physically
violent collision the stars will just
pass through each other
so they will pass through the gaps the
galaxy itself
is very large there are immense empty
spaces
so there will be no actual collisions if
if there are any actual collisions this
will be very rare
so the two galaxies will pass through
each other there will be a spiral dance
kind of
gravitational dance and eventually they
will merge into a larger
super massive galaxy and i think the
name
people have given it is milko meda or
something like that
so it will happen and
the night sky at that time will look
very different it'll be more
it will be brighter so this will happen
sometime in the next five
billion or so years so
at that time the sun will have expanded
in size it could have become a red giant
possibly by the time
and the earth will become a very much
hotter place
life as we know it today will not be
possible at that period in time
so hopefully five billion years from
today we may have moved somewhere else
if our civilization
and our species still manages to survive
so that's the kind of change that will
occur that will occur
the galaxy will become a larger combined
galaxy
it will become very much larger and much
brighter so that's what's going to
happen in about five billion years
in the future
okay let me take one more question and
then we are done
okay this is by steve jobs welcome back
steve
uh what should young people be doing
if they want india to make the most
technologically advanced nation
in the world in coming years well
the young people of india are the future
of india so it all
rests in your hands
to make india the most technologically
advanced nation in the world you have to
embrace
science and technology so i talk a lot
about our culture and history
we have to understand our cultural
industry but the way forward is through
science and technology
so we have to embrace science and
technology we have to learn the latest
technologies
we have to make ourselves proficient at
it and we have to develop our own
systems
so future of india has to be
entrepreneurship and science and
technology
so i would like the government to make
it easier for indians to become
entrepreneurs
right now it's very difficult to start a
company in your
in your garage or in your bedroom it's
very difficult for young people to do
that
so that's the first thing that needs to
happen india needs to create the right
environment
the government of india needs to make it
easy
for young entrepreneurs to start and
succeed and secondly young people
teenagers and and other people or the
young kids need to learn
the latest technologies coding
programming
web design and all these things today
it's possible to learn all of this
online for free so
you need to embrace all of this and
learn all the new emerging technologies
and let your creativity and imagination
run wild
run with it in the future the education
system is going to very soon become
obsolete
degrees will be worthless the only thing
that matters is going to be what skills
you have and what
problems can you solve with these skills
so learn skills like programming and
other in artificial intelligence
machine learning everything can be
learned online today for free
embrace technology embrace science be
grounded in your
roots in your culture we are the oldest
and most advanced civilization of all
time in the known universe
right we have always been at the
forefront of science and technology
over the past past 10 000 years so we
need to revert back to that
right so we need to embrace science and
technology and if we do that
then there is so much talent in india
india is home to the most
talented and intelligent people in the
world and the most energetic young
people in the world
so you we can all take the country
forward and
and become the greatest civilization all
over again
if we do this so that's a great question
i think we should be done
okay this is the last question absolute
last question for today kumar thank you
very much
have we measured two-way speed of light
is it possible that one-way speed of
light is different
no the speed of light is the same in any
direction
it's always the same it's a cosmic limit
that has been imposed upon this universe
there is no way of breaking this limit
even if you are sitting
hypothetically on a photon which is
going in one direction
and you encounter a photon that's coming
in the opposite direction so this guy is
moving at the speed of light and this
guy is also moving in
at the speed of light still you will see
the incoming photon
not coming at you at twice the speed of
light but only at the speed of light so
that is the kind of hard-coded cosmic
limit we have in the universe
so we have measured the speed of light
very accurately using
different technologies and it is not
possible that
the speed of light may be different in
certain directions it is a universal
limit
in our universe so thank you guys this
was a great
session thank you very much for your
participation it was great fun
and i'm going to conclude today so
tomorrow
i'm going to have a session about indian
history
come with your questions ask me anything
about indian history tomorrow and i will
answer these questions
and tomorrow i will also let you know
the schedule for the next week
what sessions we're going to have in the
next week so thank you so much for
all your questions apologies to those of
you whose questions i could not answer
but let's keep doing it and let's keep
interacting and exploring all this
knowledge
so thank you everyone and have a good
night
bye